I got up this morning at 6:10 a.m.
لقد استيقظت اليوم الساعة 6:10 صباحاً
after going to sleep at 12:45 a.m.
وكنت قد ذهبت للنوم البارحة الساعة 12:45
I was awakened once during the night.
وقد استيقظت مرة واحدة في الليل اثناء نومي
My heart rate was 61 beats per minute --
وكانت دقات قلبي 61 دقة في الدقيقة
my blood pressure, 127 over 74.
وضغط الدم 127\74
I had zero minutes of exercise yesterday,
ولم اقم بأي تمارين رياضية البارحة
so my maximum heart rate during exercise wasn't calculated.
لذا فدقات قلبي الاعظمية اثناء التمارين الرياضية لم تُحسب
I had about 600 milligrams of caffeine,
وقد تناولت 600 ملي غرام من الكافيين
zero of alcohol.
و صفراً من الكحول
And my score on the Narcissism Personality Index,
وكانت نتيجتي على مؤشر النرجسية الشخصية
or the NPI-16,
او ما يمكن تسميته ب " إن بي آي - 16 "
is a reassuring 0.31.
مطمئنة وبلغت 0.31
We know that numbers are useful for us
ان هذه الارقام مفيدة لنا
when we advertise, manage, govern, search.
عندما نُعلن .. نتحكم .. نسيطر .. نبحث
I'm going to talk about how they're useful when we reflect,
وانا سوف اتحدث اليوم عن انها مفيدة لانها تعني
learn, remember
التعلم .. والتذكر
and want to improve.
والرغبة في التطور
A few years ago, Kevin Kelly, my partner, and I
لقد لاحظنا انا وشريكي " كيفين كيلي " منذ عدة سنوات
noticed that people were subjecting themselves
ان الناس تقيم نفسها
to regimes of quantitative measurement and self-tracking
بأنظمة قياس وتعقب كمية لذواتها
that went far beyond the ordinary, familiar habits
لا كتلك التي نقوم بها بوضع اعتيادي .. او كعادة طبيعية
such as stepping on a scale every day.
مثل ان نقف على مقياس الوزن كل يوم
People were tracking their food via Twitter,
لا بل الناس بدأت بتعقب أطعمتها عن طريق " تويتر "
their kids' diapers on their iPhone.
و حفاضات أطفالها عن طريق " الآي فون "
They were making detailed journals
وهم يقومون اليوم بعمل ارشفة
of their spending, their mood,
لمصاريفهم .. ولمزاجهم
their symptoms, their treatments.
ولأعراضهم المرضية .. وعلاجاتهم الطبية
Now, we know some of the technological facts
ونحن نعلم اليوم ان بعض المعلومات التقنية
that are driving this change in our lifestyle --
سوف لامحالة تغير من نمط حياتنا
the uptake and diffusion of mobile devices,
بسبب التطور الهائل في اجهزة الهاتف المحمول
the exponential improvement in data storage
والتطول الهائل في سعة تخزين المعلومات
and data processing,
وتحليلها
and the remarkable improvement in human biometric sensors.
والتطور الهائل في اجهزة القياس الحسية والحيوية
This little black dot there
لاحظوا .. هذه النقطة السوداء الصغيرة تلك
is a 3D accelerometer.
انها جهاز قياس تسارع ثلاثي الابعاد
It tracks your movement through space.
يمكنه تعقب حركتك من الفضاء
It is, as you can see, very small and also very cheap.
وكما ترون انه صغيرٌ جدا . .وزهيد الثمن جداً
They're now down to well under a dollar a piece,
ويمكن ان تحصل على القطعة الواحدة بأقل من دولار واحد
and they're going into all kinds of devices.
وهذا ينسحب على جميع الاجهزة
But what's interesting
والامرٌ المثير للاهتمام
is the incredible detailed information that you can get
هو مقدار الكم الهائل من المعلومات
from just one sensor like this.
الذي يمكن الحصول عليها من " حساس " واحد مثل هذا
This kind of sensor
هذا المجس " الحساس "
is in the hit biometric device --
انه اليوم صرعة القياس البيولوجي
among early adopters at the moment -- the Fitbit.
من بين أوائل المتبنِّين له حالياً .. " فيت بيت "
This tracks your activity and also your sleep.
انه يقوم بتعقب وتسجيل كل نشاطك .. حتى اثناء نومك
It has just that sensor in it.
انه يقوم بقياس ذلك
You're probably familiar with the Nike+ system.
وانتم ربما تعلمون نظام " نايك بلس "
I just put it up because that little blue dot is the sensor.
وانا اعرضه امامكم لكي اريكم ان المجس " الحساس " هو النقطة الزرقاء فحسب
It's really just a pressure sensor
انها مجرد مجس " ضغط "
like the kind that's in a doorbell.
يشبه زر جرس باب المنزل
And Nike knows how to get
ومنه تقوم شركة " نايك "
your pace and distance from just that sensor.
بتحصيل معلومات وتيرة السير .. والمسافة والسرعة
This is the strap
وهذه الاسوارة
that people use to transmit heart-rate data
التي يستخدمها الاشخاص لكي ترسل معلومات دقات القلب
to their Nike+ system.
الى نظام " نايك بلس "
This is a beautiful, new device
هذ امرٌ جميل .. جهازٌ جديد
that gives you detailed sleep tracking data,
يقوم بتعقب معلومات نومك ..
not just whether you're asleep or awake, but also your phase of sleep --
ليس فحسب ان كنت مستيقظاً ام لا . .بل حتى درجات ومراحل نومك
deep sleep, light sleep, REM sleep.
اي ان كنت في نوم عميق . .خفيف .. اعتيادي
The sensor is just a little strip of metal in that headband there.
ان المجس مجرد شريحة صغيرة توضع على عصبة رأس هنا
The rest of it is the bedside console;
وباقي الامر يترك للاجهزة التي توضع بجانب السرير
just for reference, this is a sleep tracking system from just a few years ago --
ومن باب العلم ان اجهزة قياس مراحل النوم منذ مدة كانت على هذا النحو
I mean, really until now.
ولكن في يومنا هذا
And this is the sleep tracking system of today.
هكذا غدت اجهزة تعقب مراحل النوم
This just was presented
وتم عرض هذا في
at a health care conference in D.C.
معرض طبي في واشنطن العاصمة
Most of what you see there is an asthma inhaler,
ربما ستظنون انه مجرد جهاز استنشاق لمرضى الربو
but the top is a very small GPS transceiver,
ولكنه ليس كذلك .. فهو يملك جهاز تعقب " جي بي اس "
which gives you the date and location
يعطيك معلومات عن الوقت والمكان والزمن
of an asthma incident,
الذي اصبت به بنوبة ربو
giving you a new awareness
مما يعطيك وعياً
of your vulnerability
عن الاماكن التي تؤذيك .. ومدى تأثرك بها
in relation to time and environmental factors.
والعلاقة بين نوبة الربو والزمن و العوامل البيئية من حولك
Now, we know that new tools
نحن نعلم ان هذه الاجهزة الجديدة
are changing our sense of self in the world --
سوف تغير من طريقة شعورنا بالعالم من حولنا
these tiny sensors that gather data in nature,
وان هذه الاجهزة الحاساة الصغيرة التي تجمع البيانات في الطبيعة
the ubiquitous computing
والحوسبة الكلية الوجود (كل مكان وحين)
that allows that data to be understood and used,
سوف تجعل تلك المعلومات التي نحصل عليها " مفهومة " ويمكن استخدامها
and of course the social networks
وحتما ستمكن الشبكات الاجتماعية
that allow people to collaborate and contribute.
من جعل الافراد يتشاركون ويتعاونون فيما بينهم فيما يخصها
But we think of these tools as pointing outward,
ونحن اليوم نفكر بالادوات تلك وكأنها نوافذ
as windows
لعوالم جديدة
and I'd just like to invite you to think of them
ولكن انا ادعوكم لان تنظروا اليها
as also turning inward
وكأنها مرايا
and becoming mirrors.
لذواتنا تسبر دواخلنا
So that when we think about using them
ونحن نريد ان نعي ان استخدامها
to get some systematic improvement,
سوف يحسن من انفسنا
we also think about how they can be useful for self-improvement,
وان نعي ان استخدامها سوف يحسن من تطور ذواتنا
for self-discovery, self-awareness, self-knowledge.
ومن وعينا لذاتنا .. واكتشاف دواخلنا .. وفهمها
Here's a biometric device:
هذا هو جهاز قياس حيوي أيضاً
a pair of Apple Earbuds.
انها سماعات أذن من شركة " آبل "
Last year, Apple filed some patents
العام الماضي زودت آبل بعض المرضى بها
to get blood oxygenation,
لكي تحسب نسبة الدم المؤكسد
heart rate and body temperature via the Earbuds.
ودقات القلب .. وضغط الدم من خلال الاذنين فحسب !
What is this for?
لماذا كل هذا ؟
What should it be for?
لماذا صنعت آبل هذا ؟
Some people will say it's for biometric security.
بعض الناس ستقول ربما من اجل الحفاظ على الصحة
Some people will say it's for public health research.
والآخر سيقول ربما من أجل الابحاث الصحية
Some people will say it's for avant-garde marketing research.
والبعض سيقول من أجل دراسات تسويقية
I'd like to tell you
ولكن اريد ان اقول لكم
that it's also for self-knowledge.
انها من أجل " معرفة ذواتنا "
And the self isn't the only thing; it's not even most things.
فنحن - أنفسنا - لسنا شيئاً واحد . بل لسنا عدة أشياء
The self is just our operation center,
ان - ذواتنا - هي أجهزة تحكمنا
our consciousness,
هي وعينا
our moral compass.
هي بوصلتنا الاخلاقية
So, if we want to act
لذا ان ادرنا ان نتصرف
more effectively in the world,
بفاعلية اكثر في عالمنا
we have to get to know ourselves better.
علينا ان نتعرف على انفسنا أكثر
Thank you.
شُكراً لكم